EMMANUEL A. IKEKWERE

+1 5123515297 | emmaikekwere@gmail.com | LinkedIn | GitHub | United States

SUMMARY

Enthusiastic and problem-solving, a quick learner with a relentless desire for growth. I proactively take on challenges while maintaining flexibility to adapt and adjust to maintain efficiency. By employing strategy, analytical skills, adaptability, and techniques, I have worked well in analyzing and managing time across various projects leading to completion.

SKILLS and CERTIFICATIONS

Data Analysis & Visualization Tools: Power BI, Tableau, MS-Excel, Hadoop, SAS, AWS, Snowflake

Database Management Systems: MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL

Programming Languages: Python (NumPy, Pandas, SciPy, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib, TensorFlow), R, PySpark

Project Management Tools: JIRA, Microsoft Project, GitHub

Technologies: AWS Cloud, Data Warehousing, GitHub, Azure, MySQL

Machine Learning Algorithms: Clustering, Deep Learning, Anomaly Detection, Supervised Learning, Unsupervised Learning,

Natural Language Processing (NLP), Hypothesis Testing, Linear and Non-linear Optimization

Certifications: SQL Zero to Hero, Business Analysis, AWS, JIRA Fundamentals

EXPERIENCE

Data Analytics and Business and Associate (Internship)

June 2023 - Oct 2023

Balm Technologies Inc., TX, United States

- Spearheaded machine learning initiatives across cross-functional teams and achieved a 15% boost in customer retention.
- Employed SQL and Python to streamline data analysis, translating complex business problems into actionable insights that enhanced decision-making efficiency by 20%.
- Orchestrated key projects influencing data-driven strategies, leading to informed business decisions.
- Engineered automated data pipelines that improved data quality and integrity by 35%.

Information Technology Analyst (Part-Time)

Dec 2022 – Apr 2023

AI Health, TX, United States

- Leveraged machine learning algorithms to scrutinize over 1,000+ customer feedback data points, guiding data-driven decision-making for service management.
- Utilized SQL and Python to cleanse and transform raw data, making it compatible with existing systems into systemcompatible formats.
- Developed automated regression models and time-series analysis using Python and R, resulting in a 25% reduction in processing time.
- Effectively communicated findings and recommendations using the BI dashboard, leading to 3 key process improvements.

Research and Data Analyst (Full-Time)

Feb 2016 – July 2022

C7 Technologies

- Conducted deep dives into complex data sets to resolve system errors and drive improvements for 12+ business organizations, resulting in a 15% increase in business performance.
- Crafted compelling data visualizations and presentations, enhancing stakeholder understanding and decision-making.
- Translated complex business problems into algorithm solutions, providing actionable insights that informed strategic decision-making.
- Proffered data-driven solutions for 20+ personal and corporate projects, achieving 83% positive feedback and increasing retention rate by 25%.
- Mitigated project risk through effective problem-solving, ensuring data integrity and elevating project efficiency.

EDUCATION

Master of Science in Data Analytics

August 2024

Harrisburg University of Science and Technology, Harrisburg, PA

Related Coursework: Regression model and analysis, Machine learning, Exploratory Data Analysis, Predictive Analysis

Bachelor of Science in Mathematics

November 2015

University of Agriculture, Abeokuta, Ogun State

Related Coursework: Numerical Analysis, Algebra, Probability and Statistics, Operation Research, Data Structure & Algorithms

LEADERSHIP and VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

- Co-founder of IDEAL Academy, a school club encouraging problem-based teaching and self-learning.
- Mentor and Volunteer SQL Teaching Assistant for New to Tech and Coven Works Business Analysis 2023 Cohort.
- Students' Ambassador and Volunteer, Black Is Tech Conference Atlanta 2023.